<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Acronyms on PRU Portal</title>
    <link>/reference/acronym/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Acronyms on PRU Portal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/reference/acronym/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A-CDM - Airport Collaborative Decision-Making</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/a-cdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/a-cdm/</guid>
      <description> A process in which decisions related to ATFCM at airports are made based on interaction between operational stakeholders and other actors involved in ATFCM and which aims at reducing delays, improving the predictability of events and optimising the utilisation of resources.
See Also   A-CDM  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  A-CDM  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  A-CDM  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACC - Area Control Centre</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/acc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/acc/</guid>
      <description>That part of ATC that is concerned with en-route traffic coming from or going to adjacent centres or APP. It is a unit established to provide air traffic control service to controlled flights in control areas under its jurisdiction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACE - Benchmarking Report</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ace/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ace/</guid>
      <description>The ATM Cost Effectiveness (ACE) reports present yearly factual data and analysis on cost-effectiveness and productivity for Air Navigation Service Providers (ANSPs) in Europe.
The analysis focuses primarily on costs that are under ANSPs&amp;rsquo; direct control and responsibility, namely the ATM/CNS provision costs.
The reports are available on the EUROCONTROL PRC website  .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACI - Airports Council International</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/aci/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/aci/</guid>
      <description> Airports Council International (ACI) represents airports interests with Governments and international organizations, develops standards, policies and recommended practices for airports, and provides information and training opportunities to raise standards around the world.
See Also   ACI  website.  ACI Europe  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AIP - Aeronautical Information Publication</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/aip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/aip/</guid>
      <description> An AIP is a publication issued by or with the authority of a state and containing aeronautical information of a lasting character essential to air navigation.
See Also   AIP  page at Wikipedia  website.  AIP  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AIRAC - Aeronautical Information Regulation And Control</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/airac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/airac/</guid>
      <description>An AIRAC system defines a series of common dates and an associated standard aeronautical information publication procedure for States so that, for both efficiency and safety, Pilots, Air Traffic Controllers, Air Traffic Flow Managers, Flight Management Systems and Aviation Charts all are working from the same information base.
In short it defines that in all instances, information provided under the AIRAC system shall be distributed by the AIS unit at least 42 days in advance of the effective date with the objective of reaching recipients at least 28 days in advance of the effective date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AIS - Aeronautical Information Service</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ais/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ais/</guid>
      <description>A service established within the defined area of coverage responsible for the provision of aeronautical information/data necessary for the safety, regularity and efficiency of air navigation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALDT - Actual Landing Time</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/aldt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/aldt/</guid>
      <description> The actual date and time when the aircraft has landed (touch down).
See Also   Actual LanDing Time  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALoS - Acceptable Level of Safety</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/alos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/alos/</guid>
      <description> The acceptable level of safety expresses the safety goals of an oversight authority, an operator, or a services provider.
See Also   Acceptable Level of Safety  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALoSP - Acceptable Level of Safety Performance</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/alosp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/alosp/</guid>
      <description> An Acceptable level of safety performance (ALoSP) is the combination of several performance targets, that are measured using safety indicators, and the action plans needed to achieve the set targets. An ALoSP is part of both an SSP and a service provider’s [Safety Management System (SMS)]/reference/acronym/sms/.
See also   Acceptable Level of Safety  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AMAN - Arrival MANagement</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/aman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/aman/</guid>
      <description>An Arrival Manager system is primarily designed to provide automated sequencing support for the ATCOs handling traffic arriving at an airport, continuously calculating arrival sequences and times for flights, taking into account the locally defined landing rate, the required spacing for flights arriving to the runway and other criteria.
See Also   AMAN  page at SKYbrary  website.  AMAN  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  AMAN  page at EUROCONTROL  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AMC - Airspace Management Cell</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/amc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/amc/</guid>
      <description>AMC is a joint civil/military cell responsible for the day-to-day management and temporary allocation of national or sub-regional airspace under the jurisdiction of one or more ECAC state(s).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ANS - Air Navigation Service</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ans/</guid>
      <description>A generic term describing the totality of services provided in order to ensure the safety, regularity and efficiency of air navigation and the appropriate functioning of the air navigation system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ANSP - Air Navigation Services Provider</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ansp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ansp/</guid>
      <description>A body that manages flight traffic on behalf of a company, region or country.
For the list of the ANSPs considered by PRU, please refer to the ANSP&amp;rsquo;s page in the Reference section.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APP - Approach Control Office</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/app/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/app/</guid>
      <description>A unit established to provide air traffic control service to controlled flights arriving at, or departing from, one or more aerodromes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASBU - Aviation System Block Upgrade</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/asbu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/asbu/</guid>
      <description> The ASBU concept focuses on four performance improvement areas:
 airport operations; global interoperable systems and data; optimum capacity and flexible flights; efficient flight paths.  ASBUs outline the air and ground equipment and timelines for standards and procedures implementation.
See Also   ASBU  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  ASBU  page at ICAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASM - AirSpace Management</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/asm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/asm/</guid>
      <description>The process by which airspace options are selected and applied to meet the needs of the ATM community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASMA - Arrival Sequencing and Metering Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/asma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/asma/</guid>
      <description> The volume around an aerodrome taken as a reference for measuring the efficiency in handling the arrival flow. Typically it is a cylinder of 40 NM radius.
See Also  Additional ASMA time methodology in the Methodology section.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AST - Annual Summary Template</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ast/</guid>
      <description> The template for annual safety data statistics in accordance with the safety data reporting requirements documented in ESARR 2  .
See Also   ESSAR 2  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATC - Air Traffic Control</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/atc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/atc/</guid>
      <description> A service operated by the appropriate authority to promote the safe, orderly and expeditious flow of air traffic.
See Also   Air Traffic Control  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATCO - Air Traffic Control Officer</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/atco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/atco/</guid>
      <description> Air traffic controllers are people trained to maintain the safe, orderly, and expeditious flow of air traffic in the global air traffic control system.
See Also   ATCO  page at Wikipedia  website.  ATCO  page at EASA  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATFCM - Air Traffic Flow and Capacity Management</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/atfcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/atfcm/</guid>
      <description> A service complementary to Air Traffic Control (ATC), the objective of which is to optimise traffic flows according to air traffic control capacity while enabling airlines to operate safe and efficient flights.
See Also   ATFCM  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  ATFCM  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATFM - Air Traffic Flow Management</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/atfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/atfm/</guid>
      <description>A function established with the objective of contributing to a safe, orderly and expeditious flow of air traffic by ensuring that ATC capacity is utilised to the maximum extent possible, and that the traffic volume is compatible with the capacities declared by the appropriate air traffic service providers.
See Also   Air Traffic Flow Management  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  Air Traffic Flow and Capacity Management  page at ATM Lexicon  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATM - Air Traffic Management</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/atm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/atm/</guid>
      <description>A system consisting of a ground part and an air part, both of which are needed to ensure the safe and efficient movement of aircraft during all phases of operation.
The airborne part of ATM consists of the functional capability which interacts with the ground part to attain the general objectives of ATM.
The ground part of ATM comprises the functions of
 Air Traffic Services (ATS), Airspace Management (ASM), and Air Traffic Flow Management (ATFM).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATS - Air Traffic Service</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ats/</guid>
      <description>A generic term meaning variously, flight information service, alerting service, air traffic advisory service, air traffic control service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AUA - Air traffic control Unit Airspace</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/aua/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/aua/</guid>
      <description> Airspace under provision of air traffic control service.
See Also   Air Traffic Control Unit Airspace  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BADA - Base of Aircraft Data</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/bada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/bada/</guid>
      <description>The Base of Aircraft Data (BADA) is an Aircraft Performance Model developed and maintained by EUROCONTROL, with the active cooperation of aircraft manufacturers and operating airlines.
The BADA APM is designed for simulation and prediction of aircraft trajectories for purposes of ATM research and operations. Aircraft performance parameters and trajectories can be calculated using information and data contained in BADA.
To replicate reality in both operational and research modelling and simulation systems, each and every real aircraft needs a corresponding aircraft model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BLI - Basic Load Index</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/bli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/bli/</guid>
      <description>The Basic Load Index (BLI) and the Peak Load Index (PLI) were defined as indicators that enable to compare airport capacity utilisation.
Schinwald/Hornung (2014) describe a procedure to quantify the level of capacity utilisation comparing two characteristic throughput values. The BLI measures how much of the available capacity is used across the majority of the operating conditions. The PLI) is a measure for the time the airport operates traffic peaks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAA - Civil Aviation Authority</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/caa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/caa/</guid>
      <description>The governmental entity or entities, that are directly responsible for the regulation of all aspects of civil air transport, technical (i.e air navigation and aviation safety) and economic (i.e the commercial aspects of air transport).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAEP - Committee on Aviation Environmental Protection</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/caep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/caep/</guid>
      <description> The Committee on Aviation Environmental Protection is a technical committee of the ICAO Council established in 1983.
CAEP assists the Council in formulating new policies and adopting new Standards and Recommended Practices (SARPs) related to aircraft noise and emissions, and more generally to aviation environmental impact.
See Also   CAEP  page at ICAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CASA - Computer-Assisted Slot Allocation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/casa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/casa/</guid>
      <description> Part of the [ETFMS]/reference/acronym/etfms/) which provides automatic message exchange in the form of Slot Allocation Messages and other ATFCM messages.
See Also  ETFMS.  ATFCM Users Manaual  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAT - Commercial Air Transport</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cat/</guid>
      <description> An aircraft operation involving the transport of passengers, cargo or mail for remuneration or hire.
See Also   CAT  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  FAQ n.19131: What is the difference between &amp;lsquo;commercial operation&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;commercial air transport (CAT) operation&amp;rsquo;?  page at EASA  website.  CAT  page at EASA  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CCO - Continuous Climb Operation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cco/</guid>
      <description> An operation, enabled by airspace design, procedure design and ATC, in which a departing aircraft climbs without interruption, to the greatest possible extent, by employing optimum climb engine thrust, at climb speeds until reaching the cruise flight level.
See Also   CCO  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  ASBU CCO  page at ICAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CDA - Continuous Descent Approach</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cda/</guid>
      <description>An aircraft operating technique in which an arriving aircraft descends from an optimal position with minimum thrust and avoids level flight to the extent permitted by the safe operation of the aircraft and compliance with published procedures and ATC instructions.
See Also   CDA  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  CDA  page at SKYbrary  website.  CCO and CDO  page at EUROCONTROL  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CDM - Collaborative Decision Making</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cdm/</guid>
      <description> A process focused on how to decide on a course of action articulated between two or more community members.
See Also  A-CDM.  CDM  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CDO - Continuous Descent Operation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cdo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cdo/</guid>
      <description> An operation, enabled by airspace design, procedure design and ATC facilitation, in which an arriving aircraft descends continuously, to the greatest possible extent, by employing minimum engine thrust, ideally in a low drag configuration, prior to the final approach fix/final approach point.
See Also  Continuous Descent Approach.  CDO  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  CCO and CDO  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CDR - ConDitional Route</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cdr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cdr/</guid>
      <description> A non-permanent ATS route or portion thereof which is only available for flight planning and use under specified conditions.
See Also   CDR  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  CDR  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CNS - Communications, Navigation, Surveillance</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cns/</guid>
      <description> Communications, navigation and surveillance are essential technological systems, procedures and programmes for pilots in the air and air traffic controllers on the ground. They facilitate the process of establishing where the aircraft is and when and how it plans to arrive at its destination.
See Also   CNS  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CODA - Central Office for Delay Analysis</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/coda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/coda/</guid>
      <description> The Central Office for Delay Analysis within EUROCONTROL provides policy makers and managers of the ECAC Air Transport System with timely, consistent and comprehensive information on the air traffic delay situation in Europe, and to make these available to anyone with an interest in delay performance.
See Also   CODA  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPF - Correlated Position reports for a Flight</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cpf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cpf/</guid>
      <description>Flight position data derived from ATC surveillance systems (CPR).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPR - Correlated Position Report</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/cpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/cpr/</guid>
      <description> Aircraft position data derived from ATC surveillance systems.
See Also   Correlated Position Report  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  Flight Data Services  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CRCO - Central Route Charges Office</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/crco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/crco/</guid>
      <description>Airspace users which fly in the controlled airspace of EUROCONTROL’s Member States pay for the air traffic services they use.
EUROCONTROL&amp;rsquo;s Central Route Charges Office (CRCO) charges airspace users for these services on behalf of the Member States.
The CRCO calculates the route charges due to the Member States for the services provided, bills the airspace users and distributes the route charges to the States concerned.
See Also   CRCO  page at EUROCONTROL  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CTOT - Calculated Take-Off Time</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ctot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ctot/</guid>
      <description> CTOT is a tactical slot allocation time calculated to determine the time at which a flight is required to become airborne.
See Also   CTOT  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  CTOT  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DF - Distance Factor</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/df/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/df/</guid>
      <description>The distance in km (divided by 100) between the aerodrome of departure within, or the point of entry into, the airspace of the State and the aerodrome of arrival, or the point of exit from, that airspace. From the distances to be taken into account, 20 km is deducted for each take-off and landing on the territory of a member State.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC - European Commission</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ec/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ec/</guid>
      <description> The European Commission is the executive arm of the European Union and promotes its general interest.
It takes decisions on the Union&amp;rsquo;s political and strategic direction.
See Also   Mobility and Transport - Air  page at European Commission  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ECAC - European Civil Aviation Conference</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ecac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ecac/</guid>
      <description> ECAC is Europe&amp;rsquo;s largest and longest-standing aviation organisation and is part of the ICAO air transport global community.
Its mission is the promotion of the continued development of a safe, efficient and sustainable European air transport system.
See Also  ECAC-CEAC website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERNIP - European Route Network Improvement Plan</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ernip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ernip/</guid>
      <description> The European Route Network Improvement Plan is a plan developed by the Network Manager in coordination with the operational stakeholders.
It shall includes the result of Network Manager’s operational activities with respect to route network design on short and medium terms in accordance with the guiding principles of the Network Strategy Plan.
See Also   ERNIP  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESRA - EUROCONTROL Statistical Reference Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/esra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/esra/</guid>
      <description> The EUROCONTROL Statistical Reference Area is designed to include as much as possible of the ECAC area for which data are available from a range of sources within EUROCONTROL (CRCO, NM and STATFOR). It is used for high-level reports from EUROCONTROL, when referring to total Europe.
See Also   ESRA  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESSIP - European Single Sky ImPlementation plan</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/essip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/essip/</guid>
      <description> The European ATM Master Plan has three levels, with Level 3 being the implementation level. The ESSIP Plan is the Level 3 Implementation Plan.
See Also   ESSIP Objectives  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  EATM Master Plan Portal  page at SESAR  website.  European ATM Master Plan Level 3 Implementation Report  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ETFMS - Enhanced Tactical Flow Management System</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/etfms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/etfms/</guid>
      <description>The Enhanced Tactical Flow Management System is used to compare traffic demand with the available capacity of a certain air traffic control (ATC) sector. It is a key enabler of the air traffic flow and capacity management (ATFCM) services during tactical operations (on the day of the flight) and pre-tactical operations (from 1 to 6 days before the flight is airborne).
The ETFMS system has two main functions:
 Calculation of traffic demand in every sector of the NM area of operations, using the flight plan information received from the aircraft operators (AOs) via the initial flight plan processing system (IFPS)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ETS - Emissions Trading Scheme</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ets/</guid>
      <description> The objective of the EU ETS is to reduce greenhouse gas emissions in a cost-effective way and contribute to meeting the EU’s Kyoto Protocol targets.
See Also   EU ETS  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  EU ETS  page at European Commission  website.  Kyoto Protocal  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FAB - Functional Airspace Block</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fab/</guid>
      <description> An airspace block based on operational requirements and established regardless of State boundaries, where the provision of air navigation services and related functions are performance-driven and optimised with a view to introducing enhanced cooperation among air navigation service providers or, where appropriate, an integrated provider.
See Also  FAB definition.  FAB  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FIR - Flight Information Region</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fir/</guid>
      <description> An airspace of defined dimensions within which flight information service and alerting service are provided.
See Also   FIR  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FL - Flight Level</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fl/</guid>
      <description>Altitude above sea level in 100 feet units measured according to a standard atmosphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FMP - Flow Management Position</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fmp/</guid>
      <description> A working position established in appropriate air traffic control units to ensure the necessary interface with a central management unit on matters concerning the provision of the air traffic flow management service.
See Also   FMP  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FRA - Free Route Airspace</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fra/</guid>
      <description>FRA refers to a specified airspace within which users may freely plan a route between a defined entry point and a defined exit point, with the possibility to route via intermediate (published or unpublished) way points, without reference to the ATS route network, subject to airspace availability. Within this airspace, flights remain subject to air traffic control.
Free route airspace implementation status December 2016  See Also   FRA  page at EUROCONTROL  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FTFM - Filed Tactical Flight Model</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ftfm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ftfm/</guid>
      <description> A mathematical model containing a point and airspace volume profile created in ETFMS for a flight when Flight plan details, and any subsequent changes, are received from Network Operations.
See Also  ETFMS.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FUA - Flexible Use of Airspace</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/fua/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/fua/</guid>
      <description> FUA concept is based on the fundamental principle that airspace is one continuum (i.e. no longer designated as purely &amp;ldquo;civil&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;military&amp;rdquo;) to be allocated for use on a day-to-day basis to accommodate user requirements.
See Also   FUA  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GA - General Aviation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ga/</guid>
      <description> All civil aviation operations other than scheduled air services and non-scheduled air transport operations for remuneration or hire.
See Also  OAT. GAT.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GANP - Global Air Navigation Plan</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ganp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ganp/</guid>
      <description> The GANP is a strategic document for regional and national planning for air navigation infrastructure.
See Also   GANP - Capacity and Efficiency (PDF)  page at ICAO  website.  GANP resources  page at ICAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GAT - General Air Traffic</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/gat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/gat/</guid>
      <description> GAT encompasses all flights conducted in accordance with the rules and procedures of [ICAO][icao].
See Also  GA. OAT.  GAT and OAT  page at IVAO  website..  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GCD - Great-Circle Distance</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/gcd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/gcd/</guid>
      <description> The great-circle distance or orthodromic distance is the shortest distance between two points on the surface of a sphere, measured along the surface of the sphere.
See Also   Great-Circle Distance  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IATA - International Air Transport Association</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/iata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/iata/</guid>
      <description> The International Air Transport Association is a trade association of the world’s airlines. It supports airline activity and helps formulate industry policy and standards.
See Also   IATA    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICAO - International Civil Aviation Organization</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/icao/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/icao/</guid>
      <description> The International Civil Aviation Organization is an agency of the United Nations. It codifies the principles and techniques of international air navigation and fosters the planning and development of international air transport to ensure safe and orderly growth.
See Also   ICAO    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IFPS - Initial Flight Plan Processing System</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ifps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ifps/</guid>
      <description>IFPS collects, processes and distributes flight plans covering part of the ICAO EUR Region known as the IFPS Zone (IFPZ).
IFPS consolidates the flight plans of the Network Manager area of operations (IFPZ) into a single repository, thus maximising the consistency of flight data available operationally.
See Also   Flight planning domain  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  Flight plan filing and management  page at EUROCONTROL  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IFR - Instrument Flight Rules</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ifr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ifr/</guid>
      <description>Instrument flight rules (IFR) is one of two sets of regulations governing all aspects of civil aviation aircraft operations; the other is visual flight rules (VFR).
Instrument flight rules are rules and regulations to govern flight under conditions in which flight by outside visual reference is not safe. IFR flight depends upon flying by reference to instruments in the flight deck, and navigation is accomplished by reference to electronic signals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IMC - Instrument Meteorological Conditions</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/imc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/imc/</guid>
      <description> Instrument meteorological conditions is an aviation flight category that describes weather conditions that require pilots to fly primarily by reference to instruments, and therefore under IFR.
See Also   IMC  page at Wikipedia  website. IFR.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JC - Just culture</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/jc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/jc/</guid>
      <description>The EUROCONTROL definition of “just culture”, also adopted by other European aviation stakeholders, is a culture in which “front line operators or others are not punished for actions, omissions or decisions taken by them that are commensurate with their experience and training, but where gross negligence, wilful violations and destructive acts are not tolerated.”</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KEA - Key performance Environment indicator based on Actual trajectory</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/kea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/kea/</guid>
      <description> KEA is the horizontal flight efficiency indicator calculated using the trajectories generated via radar data.
See Also  HFE in the Methodology section.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KEP - Key performance Environment indicator based on last filed flight Plan</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/kep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/kep/</guid>
      <description> KEP is the horizontal flight efficiency indicator calculated using the last filed flight plans to describe the trajectories.
See Also  HFE in the Methodology section.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KPA - Key Performance Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/kpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/kpa/</guid>
      <description> KPAs are a way of categorizing performance subjects related to high-level ambitions and expectations.
See Also   KPA  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KPI - Key Performance Indicator</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/kpi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/kpi/</guid>
      <description>A quantitative measure to express current, past or expected future performance as well as actual progress in achieving performance objectives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LAQ - Local Air Quality</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/laq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/laq/</guid>
      <description>Formerly Local Convergence and Implementation Plans</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LSSIP - Local Single Sky ImPlementation plans/reports</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/lssip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/lssip/</guid>
      <description>Formerly Local Convergence and Implementation Plans</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTO - Landing and Take-off cycle</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/lto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/lto/</guid>
      <description> LTO cycle is defined by ICAO. It covers four modes of engine operation, namely idle, approach, climb out and take-off, each of which is associated with a specific engine thrust setting and a time in mode.
See Also   Advanced Emission Model  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MET - METeorological services for air navigation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/met/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/met/</guid>
      <description> Those facilities and services that furnish aviation with meteorological forecasts, briefs and observations.
See Also   MET  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>METAR - METeorological Aerodrome or Aeronautical Report</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/metar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/metar/</guid>
      <description> METAR is a format for reporting weather information typically from airports or permanent weather observation stations.
See Also   METAR  page at Wikipedia  website.  METAR  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MTOW - Maximum Take-Off Weight</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/mtow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/mtow/</guid>
      <description> The MTOW of an aircraft is the maximum mass, defined by the aircraft manufacturer (due to structural or other limits), at which the aircraft is certified for take off.
See Also   MTOW  page at Wikipedia  website.  MTOW  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NM - Nautical Mile</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/nm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/nm/</guid>
      <description> An International System of Units&amp;rsquo; unit of measurement defined as exactly 1852 meters.
See Also   NM  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NM - Network Manager</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/nm-cfmu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/nm-cfmu/</guid>
      <description> The Network Manager addresses performance issues strategically, operationally and technically. Its overarching mission is to contribute to the delivery of air traffic management’s (ATM) performance in the pan-European network in the areas of safety, capacity, environment/flight efficiency and cost-effectiveness.
See Also   NM  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NOP - Network Operations Plan</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/nop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/nop/</guid>
      <description> The plan, including its supporting tools, developed by the [Network Manager][nm-cfmu] in coordination with the operational stakeholders to organise its operational activities in the short and medium term in accordance with the guiding principles of the Network Strategic Plan.
See Also   NOP  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  NOP  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NOTAM - NOTices to AirMen</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/notam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/notam/</guid>
      <description> A Notice to Airmen is a notice filed with an aviation authority to alert aircraft pilots of potential hazards along a flight route or at a location that could affect the safety of the flight.
See Also   NOTAM  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OAT - Operational Air Traffic</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/oat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/oat/</guid>
      <description> All flights, which do not comply with the provisions stated for GAT and for which rules and procedures have been specified by appropriate national authorities.
Most OAT flights are operated by military agencies.
See Also  GAT.  GAT and OAT  page at IVAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLI - Peak Load Index</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/pli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/pli/</guid>
      <description>The Peak Load Index (PLI) and the Basic Load Index (BLI) were defined as indicators that enable to compare airport capacity utilisation.
Schinwald/Hornung (2014) describe a procedure to quantify the level of capacity utilisation comparing two characteristic throughput values. The PLI is a measure for the time the airport operates traffic peaks. The BLI measures how much of the available capacity is used across the majority of the operating conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PRC - Performance Review Commission</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/prc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/prc/</guid>
      <description>The Performance Review Commission (PRC) was established in 1998 by the Permanent Commission of EUROCONTROL. It provides objective information and independent advice to EUROCONTROL’s Governing Bodies on European Air Traffic Management Performance, based on extensive research, data analysis and consultation with stakeholders.
Its purpose is &amp;ldquo;to ensure the effective management of the European Air Traffic Management System through a strong, transparent and independent performance review,&amp;rdquo; as stated in Article 1 of the PRC Terms of Reference and Rules of Procedure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PRISME - Pan European Repository of Information Supporting the Management of EATM</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/prisme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/prisme/</guid>
      <description>A comprehensive repository of European aviation data including but not limited to flight plans, flight trajectories, airspace structures, flight delays, fleet information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PRR - Performance Review Report</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/prr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/prr/</guid>
      <description> A pubblication of the PRC which analyses the performance of the European Air Traffic Management System.
See Also   PRC Publications  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PRU - Performance Review Unit</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/pru/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/pru/</guid>
      <description> The PRU is responsible for monitoring and reviewing the performance of the European ANS System. Based on its analysis, the PRU supports the PRC in improving the performance of the European ANS system.
Organisationally, PRU is part of the EUROCONTROL Single Sky Directorate.
See Also  About PRU.  PRU  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RAD - Route Availability Document</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/rad/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/rad/</guid>
      <description>The Route Availability Document is a flight-planning document, which integrates both structural and ATFCM requirements, geographically and vertically, following an appropriate collaborative decision making process between the [network manager][nm] and the operational stakeholders. It is a &amp;lsquo;central&amp;rsquo; source of airspace utilisation rules and availability defined and communicated by the ANSPs, 56 days before the start of the concerned Aeronautical Information Regulation and Control (AIRAC) cycle.
It facilitates flight planning in order to improve Air traffic Flow and Capacity Management while allowing aircraft operators&amp;rsquo; flight planning flexibility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RAT - Risk Analysis Tool for safety</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/rat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/rat/</guid>
      <description> The Risk Analysis Tool is a methodology used to classify safety related occurrences in the ATM domain.
See Also   RAT  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RI - Runway Incursion</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ri/</guid>
      <description> Runway Incursion is defined as &amp;ldquo;any unauthorised presence on a runway of aircraft, vehicle, person or object where an avoiding action was required to prevent a collision with an aircraft.&amp;ldquo;
See Also   RI  page at SKYbrary  website.  RI  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RP1 - Reporting Period 1</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/rp1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/rp1/</guid>
      <description> The Reporting Period 1 of the SES Performance Scheme for EU and associated States covers the years 2012-2014.
See Also  SES.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RP2 - Reporting Period 2</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/rp2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/rp2/</guid>
      <description> The Reporting Period 2 of the SES Performance Scheme for EU and associated States covers the years 2015-2019.
See Also  SES.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RVSM - Reduced Vertical Separation Minima</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/rvsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/rvsm/</guid>
      <description> A reduction to 1000 feet vertical separation between flights, which is used in Europe and on the North Atlantic, between FL290 and FL410.
See Also   European RVSM Approvals  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SES - Single European Sky</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ses/</guid>
      <description>The EU’s SES main objective is to reform ATM in Europe in order to cope with sustained air traffic growth and operations under the safest, most cost- and flight-efficient and environmentally friendly conditions. This implies de-fragmenting the European airspace, reducing delays, increasing safety standards and flight efficiency to reduce the aviation environmental footprint, and reducing costs related to service provision.
See Also   SES  page at European Commission  website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SESAR - Single European Sky ATM Research programme</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/sesar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/sesar/</guid>
      <description> SESAR coordinates and concentrates all EU research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities in ATM, pooling together a wealth experts to develop the new generation of ATM.
See Also   SESAR    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SID - Standard Instrument Departure</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/sid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/sid/</guid>
      <description> A Standard Instrument Departure Route is a standard ATS route identified in an instrument departure procedure by which aircraft should proceed from take-off phase to the en-route phase.
See Also   SID and STAR  page at SKYbrary  website. STAR  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SM - Separation Minima</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/sm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/sm/</guid>
      <description>Separation Minima is the minimum required distance between aircraft. Vertically usually 1000 feet below flight level 290, 2000 feet above flight level 290. Horizontally, depending on the radar, 3 NM or more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SMI - Separation Minima Infringement</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/smi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/smi/</guid>
      <description>Separation Minima Infringement is a situation in which prescribed separation minima were not maintained between aircraft.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SMS - Safety Management System</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/sms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/sms/</guid>
      <description> Safety Management System (SMS) - A systematic and explicit approach defining the activities by which safety management is undertaken by an organisation in order to achieve acceptable or tolerable safety.
See Also   SMS  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SRC - Safety Regulation Commission</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/src/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/src/</guid>
      <description> The Safety Regulation Commission advises the Permanent Commission of EUROCONTROL, through the Provisional Council, on all matters related to the safety regulation of ATM, and provides recommendations and specific proposals for the improvement of the safety of these services.
See Also   SRC  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSC - Single Sky Committee</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ssc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ssc/</guid>
      <description>The Single Sky Committee has been established to support the European Commission in the implementation of the Single European Sky.
It is composed by two representatives of each European Union Member State (civil and military) and observers from third countries and EUROCONTROL.
Each Member State delegation is considered to be one committee member. The SSC is chaired by a representative from the European Commission. The Chairman may decide to invite experts to talk on particular matters, at the request of a member or on his/her own initiative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSP - State Safety Programme</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/ssp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/ssp/</guid>
      <description> An integrated set of regulations and activities aimed at improving safety.
See Also   SSP  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STAM - Short Term ATFCM Measures</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/stam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/stam/</guid>
      <description> An approach to smooth sector workloads by reducing traffic peaks through short-term application of minor ground delays, appropriate flight level capping and exiguous rerouting to a limited number of flights.
See also   STAM  page at ATM Lexicon  website. STAM definition.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STAR - Standard Arrival Route</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/star/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/star/</guid>
      <description> A Standard Arrival Route is a standard ATS route identified in an approach procedure by which aircraft should proceed from the en-route phase to an initial approach fix.
See Also   SID and STAR  page at SKYbrary  website. STAR  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STATFOR - Statistics and Forecast Service</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/statfor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/statfor/</guid>
      <description> STATFOR provides statistics and forecasts on air traffic in Europe and to monitor and analyse the evolution of the Air Transport Industry.
See Also   STATFOR  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SU - Service Unit</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/su/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/su/</guid>
      <description> The multiplication of aircraft weight factor by distance factor.
See Also   CRCO  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SUA - Special Use Airspace</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/sua/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/sua/</guid>
      <description> Airspace of defined dimensions identified by an area on the surface of the earth wherein activities must be confined because of their nature and/or wherein limitations may be imposed upon aircraft operations that are not a part of those activities.
See Also   SUA  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TBS - Time Based Separation</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tbs/</guid>
      <description> The separation of aircraft using time intervals instead of distances.
See Also   TBS  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TCZ - Terminal Charging Zone</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tcz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tcz/</guid>
      <description> An airport or a group of airports for which a single cost-base and a single unit rate are established.
See Also  Terminal ANS Unit Rate definition.  CRCO - What are route charges  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  TCZ  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TMA - Terminal Manoeuvring Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tma/</guid>
      <description> TMA is designated area of controlled airspace surrounding a major airport where there is a high volume of traffic.
See Also   TMA  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TNC - Terminal Navigation Charges</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tnc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tnc/</guid>
      <description> Given the risk for potential misunderstanding, it is useful to differentiate between Terminal ANS charges (also called “TNC” for terminal navigation charges) and “Airport charges”, which typically include landing, passenger, cargo, parking and hangar, and noise charges, and are covered by the EU Directive on airport charges (Directive 2009/12/EC).
See also  Terminal ANS Unit Rate definition.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TNSU - Terminal Navigation Service Units</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tnsu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tnsu/</guid>
      <description> The costs for the provision of terminal air navigation services.
See Also  Terminal ANS Unit Rate definition.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TOBT - Target Off-Block Time</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tobt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tobt/</guid>
      <description>The time that an aircraft operator / handling agent estimates that an aircraft will be ready, all doors closed, boarding bridge removed, push back vehicle present, ready to start up / push back immediately upon reception of clearance from the TWR.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TRA - Temporary Reserved Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tra/</guid>
      <description> A defined volume of airspace normally under the jurisdiction of one aviation authority and temporarily reserved, by common agreement, for the specific use by another aviation authority and through which other traffic may be allowed to transit, under ATC clearance.
See Also   TRA  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  TRA  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TSA - Temporary Segregated Area</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/tsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/tsa/</guid>
      <description> A defined volume of airspace normally under the jurisdiction of one aviation authority and temporarily segregated, by common agreement, for the exclusive use by another aviation authority and through which other traffic will not be allowed to transit.
See Also   TSA  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  TSA  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWR - ToWeR</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/twr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/twr/</guid>
      <description>A unit established to provide air traffic control service to aerodrome traffic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UAC - Upper Area Control centre</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/uac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/uac/</guid>
      <description> An ACC centre providing seamless air navigation services to the upper airspace.
See Also  ACC.  Upper Airspace  page at ATM Lexicon  website.  MUAC  page at EUROCONTROL  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UPA - Unauthorised Penetration of Airspace</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/upa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/upa/</guid>
      <description> Unauthorised penetration of airspace (also known as Airspace Infringement). The penetration by an aircraft into a portion of airspace without prior permission of the appropriate authorities (when such prior permission is required).
See Also   UPA  page at SKYbrary  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>USOAP - Universal Safety Oversight Audit Programme</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/usoap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/usoap/</guid>
      <description> A framewok developed by ICAO to evaluate the safety oversight capabilities of its Member States and achieve a more comprehensive understanding of this crucial component to air transport’s continued growth and development.
See Also   USOAP  page at SKYbrary  website.  USOAP  page at ICAO  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VFR - Visual Flight Rules</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/vfr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/vfr/</guid>
      <description> Visual flight rules are a set of regulations under which a pilot operates an aircraft in weather conditions generally clear enough to allow the pilot to see where the aircraft is going.
See Also   VFR  page at Wikipedia  website.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WF - Weight Factor</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/wf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/wf/</guid>
      <description> The square root of the result obtained by dividing the maximum take-off weight (in metric tons) of the aircraft by 50.
See Also  MTOW.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>XMAN - CROSS border arrival MANagement</title>
      <link>/reference/acronym/xman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/reference/acronym/xman/</guid>
      <description>Cross-Border Arrival Management, also referred to as Extended Arrival Management, is an operational procedure which aims to improve and optimise arrival management operations for major airports.
The aircraft’s holding time at congested airports is cut by reducing their cruising speed during the final en-route phase of flight, several hundred miles away from the airport. In doing so, flight efficiency is increased by reducing the overall fuel burn and CO2 emissions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>